I know we had to solve the
problem here,
too.
I know we had to solve the
problem here,
too.
I know we had to solve the
problem here, too.
problem here,
too.
I know we had to solve the
problem here, too.
problem here,
too.
I know we had to solve the
problem here, too.
problem here,
too.
I know we had to solve the
problem here, too.
He's not gonna do it
Okay
It's just after 10.30,
so we'll get started.
Welcome, everyone, to the first
lecture of EECS 245 this fall.
I will usually start lectures
with just an agenda of what we
plan on covering today.
Normally, they will have much
more regular content than this
has.
But I think it makes sense to
start with some introductions
before we talk about what
machine learning is and what
about machine learning we are
going to study in this class.
Then we will talk about some
logistics,
some of which are slightly
different this semester than
previous offerings.
and then we will get into our
actual content.
So first a little bit about me.
My name is Suraj Rampure.
You can just call me by my first
name Suraj.
This is my third year teaching
at Michigan and it's my fourth
time teaching this class, EECS
245.
So I created this class last
fall, taught it last fall,
winter in the spring and this is
now the fourth offering.
This fall I'm actually also
teaching another class in the
math department on central
campus which is I'll have to
rush after office hours that I
have after lectures, but we're
developing with the College of
Engineering And the math
department is a like new
first-year sequence kind of like
engineering 10101 specifically
for
Math for engineering students.
So in that class, which is
called math 124 I'm actually
co-teaching it with a math
professor and it's like sort of
like this class because it's
also linear algebra But unlike
this class it's designed for
people who have no prior
calculus or discrete math or any
experience So it's designed for
first year, first semester
freshmen.
So I'm pretty excited about that
as well,
though this class is my baby, so
I'm very excited about it as
well.
Before coming to Michigan, I
used to teach at UCSD,
and before that, I was a student
at Berkeley.
It's not just me who you are
going to work with in this
class.
You have two TAs,
one of whom will be your lab TA,
and you will meet them in lab
tomorrow,
and you will also meet both of
them throughout office hours.
So I wanted to give them both a
chance to introduce themselves.
Yeah, I'm a third year CS
undergrad and I'm excited to be
in Iowa this semester if you're
coming to the 1230 lab, you'll
see me there.
Also, please come by in office
hours,
I promise we're all very nice
people,
so please come even though if
you don't have any questions and
we're excited to get to know
you.
Hi everyone,
my name is Todul,
I'm a second year PhD student in
CSE,
so yeah,
excited to be able to commit to
you and hope to see you guys in
the lab.
Awesome.
Okay,
first day of class we'll do a
little bit of an icebreaker and
the icebreaker is sort of meant
to get you to talking with the
other people near you and for
you to learn a little bit more
about me.
So we're going to play four
truths and a lie.
Four of these statements are
true about me, one of them is
not true.
What I want you to do is discuss
with the people near you,
introduce yourselves to them,
get contact information if you
don't already have it, and try
and figure out which one of
these is a lie.
Discuss.
I should hear lots of talking.
We'll be back.
I was thinking, no idea man,
your sign's major now.
I'd say it's pretty fair,
but it doesn't get that bad.
Because you can't really do the
mushroom,
but he's like a friend,
and having all of his fun.
Definitely like that stuff.
I think it's alright having a
roundhouse.
I think he's just really into
it.
Yeah, he's pretty into it.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's hard for me to do it.
I don't know.
I'm also not a U.S.
assistant,
so it's really good for us.
...yourself.
That's what I remember.
Like if you step,
you don't have to step.
That's the thing though, that
was the crazy truth.
Some like...
So good.
That's a good idea.
...especially
for a guy who grew up in this
summer,
I don't know if he's an
integrated or not,
but he's a really good guy.
OK, let's come back together.
Let's see,
let's get a show of hands.
How many people think the first
one is a lie? I skipped a grade.
Couple of people.
How many people think the second
is a lie? I have two kids.
In about half the class.
Third,
Soulja Boy used to follow me on
Twitter.
A couple of people think that's
a lie.
Fourth,
I got into Michigan when I
applied for undergrad.
And fifth, I'm not a US citizen.
The lie is this.
I have no kids.
But in my mind, I'm way too
young to have kids.
I'm only 27.
But I'm going to keep using this
until people start to think I do
have kids.
But these are all true.
I skipped a grade, skipped first
grade, nothing special.
To explain that, I'm not a US
citizen, I'm Canadian actually.
I'm actually from Windsor.
Has anyone here been to Windsor?
Yeah, a couple people.
There's not much to do there
unless you're going to Toronto
or it's your 19th birthday,
but yeah, that's a big reason
why I moved from UCSC to
Michigan to be closer to family
in Windsor, though Michigan is
obviously a great school as
well.
Let's see, I got into Michigan
when I applied for undergrad,
that is true.
Got denied Ross pre-admit
though, if they still do that.
And Soulja Boy used to follow me
on Twitter, that is also true.
The first dollar I ever made was
through YouTube AdSense, making
YouTube videos when I was in
seventh grade,
and this was related to that.
You can come to office hours if
you want to learn more about
that.
But this,
no, not true.
Okay,
just a little bit more about me,
these are some pictures I took
over the summer.
I spent a lot of time this
summer developing materials for
this new math class that we're
teaching.
Not enough time doing that.
Most of my time was spent
biking,
walking,
eating,
traveling.
Here's a picture of my dog.
He actually may be older than
some of you.
He was born in 2009,
but he's still doing okay.
This is a picture from Oxford.
They have a blackboard that
Einstein wrote on and they like
preserved it, which I thought
was pretty cool.
The Grease this past summer,
there was a little exhibit where
you could make olive oil.
You press the olives yourself,
and the juice comes out, which
is pretty cool.
And yeah,
it was just a little bit about
me.
And over the course of the
semester, I want to learn a
little bit more about each and
every one of you as well.
So don't be a stranger.
Come to office hours, say hi,
ask about these random things,
tell me more about yourself.
I'll get on this soapbox
throughout the lecture, but in
my view, part of the point of
coming to a school like Michigan
isn't so much like the quality
of the specific homework
problems you get to work on,
even though those are good too.
Everything about this class is
publicly available online.
Anyone could just go to
EECS245.org,
watch the lectures, do the
homework.
The point of coming to a place
like Michigan is taking
advantage of the human
resources.
That's the other people who are
here, that's your instructors,
your TAs, so I really want you
to take advantage of the human
community in this class and in
your other classes here at the
school.
So that's a little bit about me.
Like I said, I want to start by
giving you a broad sense of what
machine learning is about,
and then talk about some of the
more boring logistics.
And to illustrate what machine
learning is about,
what I'm going to do is go to
our course notes, which maybe
you've read about if you've
taken a look at the syllabus.
This is chapter 1.1
if you have your computer open,
though you don't need to.
What I have here is a box in
which, you can do this with your
mouse as well, I'm gonna try and
draw with my iPad.
In this box you can draw a
digit.
Let's try it.
I'm gonna draw four.
Okay, nothing special there.
If you scroll down, what you're
seeing here is a model is trying
to guess what digit I wrote.
And what it's showing me with
these bars is the probability,
according to the model that what
I drew was a zero,
a one, a two, a three, a four,
five, six, seven, eight, or
nine.
And what did you notice with
this four?
What do you notice?
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Yeah.
Allison.
Thinks it's an eight.
It thinks it's an eight.
Yeah, exactly.
The most likely outcome
according to the model was that
this was an eight.
It thinks, OK, maybe it could be
a four or five, but it seemed
like greater than a 50% chance
that it's an 8.
What if I draw my 4 this way?
It still is sort of split
between a 4 and an 8, but now it
starts to think it's a 9.
What if I draw a 9 like that?
It looks kind of like the 4 that
I just drew,
but it's pretty confident that
this is a 9.
What if I draw a 1 there?
It thinks it's a 1.
What if I draw the 1 over here?
Now it starts to think a little
bit that it's a seven.
What if I draw a zero here?
Well, it's pretty confident that
it's a two.
So what we're seeing is that
sometimes this model works
well, and sometimes it doesn't
work well.
And I encourage you to play
around with this and see if you
can fool it in weird ways.
Like there it thinks it's a
nine.
It thinks this zero is a nine?
Yeah,
everyone else have your name?
Gavin?
That's where if you were going
to complete the nine, and that's
where the hoop would be.
Exactly.
If we were to draw a nine,
that's what it would look like.
But maybe if I start up here,
I can get it to think it's an
eight as well.
So this example of handwritten
digit classification
is actually one of the first
examples of a machine learning
system that was employed by
society at large.
And it was actually developed by
USPS in the late 1990s to
transcribe the addresses people
wrote on letters.
Okay, I haven't personally sent
a letter before,
many of you probably haven't
either, but,
you know, if you need to mail
something anywhere,
before you would go, now you go
to the post office and if you
have to send a package, you tell
them the address and they type
it in.
But before you would write a
letter and USPS developed this,
or they didn't develop it, but
they used this technology
to figure out who to send their
packages to.
And this is an example of a
machine learning system.
Now,
what I want to illustrate here
is what makes this a machine
learning system.
If you had to develop a system
like this on your own to figure
out what digit is written down,
one way you could do this is to
come up with a massive set of if
statements.
You could say things like,
if there's a circle,
well, then it could be an 8,
but it could be a 0.
Or maybe it's a 2 with the loop
at the bottom.
Or maybe it's a 9.
If there's a stick,
well, then maybe it's a 1.
maybe it's a seven,
you know, maybe it's a nine.
You could come up with a bunch
of if statements like that.
But what's the problem with that
approach?
What's the problem with just
writing hundreds of if
statements? Yes, and remind us
of your name?
Ammar.
I think it's just like tedious.
Yeah, it's tedious.
And here there are only 10
possible categories or classes,
zero through nine.
But what if we were trying to
figure out what letter people
wrote?
Then there are 26 options,
why stop at letters and numbers?
What if we were trying to figure
out what animal we took a
picture of? How would you write
if statements that accurately
capture all of that
sophistication?
So that approach that I just
described of writing a bunch of
if statements,
that is not the machine learning
approach.
OK? Instead, the machine
learning approach
is to start with a data set,
OK?
And what you do is you start
with a data set.
And in this example,
you start with a data set that
is labeled,
or in other words, a data set in
which you know the right answers
already.
That's what a label is.
So to train this handwritten
digit classifier,
what we did, or what they did,
is it took lots of images of
zeros that people wrote and
wrote down, okay, these are all
zeros,
and then took lots of pictures
of ones that people wrote and
said, okay, these are pictures
of ones, and these are pictures
of twos, and these are pictures
of threes.
And so what we do is we show the
system lots of labeled examples
of what each category is
supposed to look like, and the
idea is that the system
automatically learns how to
distinguish ones from twos from
threes and fours.
Okay, And as we see,
it doesn't necessarily do this
perfectly,
but that is the machine learning
approach.
And by developing better machine
learning models, we build
systems that are more accurately
able to do things like classify
handwritten digits.
But that's the core idea I
wanted to impart here.
The machine learning approach to
solving
problems This is about
automatically
recognizing patterns in
data.
And this definition of machine
learning,
automatically recognizing
patterns in data,
applies to other sort of systems
that you've heard about in
popular media that involve
machine learning and artificial
intelligence.
ChatGPT,
I think you're all pretty aware
that what it does
is it tries to regurgitate
things that sound similar to
what it saw in its training
data, which is why it's pretty
obvious when someone has just
copy-pasted output from Claude.
And it's because most of the
ChatGPT and Claude and Gemini
outputs sound very similar
because they're trying to mimic
patterns that they've already
seen.
And to create these systems,
they used trillions of gigabytes
of data,
and that's why they seem to know
about so many different things.
Now, it's not just that,
right?
Tools like Chachi Bhati also
have the ability to look things
up on the internet,
so if it didn't already know
about something, it can learn
about it.
But that's the crux of it.
Out of curiosity, how many
people here knew that the person
that Claude is named after went
to Michigan?
So Claude is named after a
famous mathematician computer
scientist from the 1930s named
Claude Shannon.
And he's like,
he's not super like,
people say he's like Einstein or
Newton level genius but just
doesn't have the PR that those
people had.
But there's actually a statue of
him on North Campus in front of
the expo.
You should go look at it and
it'll say Claude Shannon.
And if you search him up, you'll
see that he developed a lot of
the foundational theories used
in machine learning and AI.
And that's who Anthropic named
the system after.
And he went to Michigan for his
master's and PhD.
Okay,
so we're comfortable with my
definition of machine learning,
automatically recognizing
patterns in data.
Okay,
so what I want to give us is a
broad understanding of the types
of problems one can solve using
machine learning.
And maybe this is a slightly
outdated approach because
something like ChatGPT doesn't
directly fit into this taxonomy,
but I'll talk about that in just
a little bit.
But for the most part, our focus
is going to be on a smaller
sliver of machine learning, and
we will start from there and
build your foundation from
there.
OK.
For us,
I want to look here into these
two broad categories
of supervised learning and
unsupervised learning.
The key difference is that with
supervised learning,
we have labeled data.
Can you tell me what labeled
data is? I just mentioned it,
but I want to hear it in your
own words.
What is labeled data?
Gavin.
When we were doing the numbers,
we categorized all the zeros
into one group and all the ones.
We didn't just throw them all in
randomly.
Exactly.
You want to add to that and
remind us of your name?
I'm Drew.
There's like a direct answer.
Exactly.
We know the right answer.
So in label data,
we know
the right answer.
So if we have all of the answers
already, why are we trying to
predict anything in the first
place?
What's the point?
Predict stuff that's not in your
data set already.
Exactly, the whole point is to
use this data set that we've
collected to learn patterns so
that we can go and make
predictions when we don't
already know the right answer.
When I went to that handwritten
digit classification box and
started drawing my own ones and
twos and threes,
the people who made that system
30 years ago didn't know what I
was going to draw.
So they don't already know what
I was going to draw.
What they tried to do is use the
data they had access to to build
as accurate of a system as they
could.
So that's ultimately the point
of building a machine learning
model.
You use the data that you've
collected
to build a model that you think
will work well in the future
when you don't already know the
right answer.
So I like thinking of supervised
learning problems as sort of
problems of the form predict y
given
x, okay.
That's a supervised learning
problem.
Your data set has some x's and
y's and what you want to do is
come up with a way to predict y
from x.
Within supervised learning there
are two broad sort of subgroups.
Regression and classification.
Can someone tell me the
difference if you happen to have
heard of these terms before.
What is regression and what is
classification?
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Charlie.
Regression is to predict a value
based
on the past patterns of the
data, and classification is to
give a class of a data used to
do prediction.
Exactly.
You're on the right track.
Both regression and
classification
are problems in which the form
is predict y from x.
The difference is that with
regression,
y is numerical,
or continuous,
versus in classification,
y is a category.
Okay,
so that handwritten digit
example,
was that regression or
classification?
It's a little ambiguous.
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Alex.
It's classification.
Why?
Even though we were predicting
numbers.
Because there are only 10 values
that can be.
Yeah, and remind us of your
name?
Gray.
Yeah.
So the handwritten digit example
is a little ambiguous, but it's
clearly classification, even
though it seems like we're
predicting numbers.
And it's because those numbers
in that case were just symbols
that we needed to predict.
OK, they just happen to look
like numbers.
But if instead I change the
problem to predictive this is an
ABCDEFG or H.
It's the same thing
mathematically The symbols just
look different.
So it should be categorized the
same way in this taxonomy.
Okay?
So things like predicting a
handwritten digit or predicting
true or false.
It's going to snow tomorrow or
Predicting this is pictures of a
cat dog hamster or zebra.
Those are all
classification tasks
Regression tasks are ones where
the variable we are predicting
is some continuous numerical
variable,
like predicting what grade you
are going to get on the final
exam using your midterm one and
midterm two grades.
That's a regression problem.
Or say the running example we
are going to use this semester,
and we will start with that at
the end of today's lecture, is
predicting how long it's going
to take for you to get to work
tomorrow given various factors
about your commute.
Right there, we're predicting a
commute time in minutes, OK?
So are we clear on the
difference between regression
and classification?
OK,
most of our semester is going to
be spent here
on regression problems.
But that's just because I've
created this story that
introduces all of the linear
algebra ideas we need so that it
helps us solve this regression
problem.
But that foundation we build
will equally apply to all of
these other branches of machine
learning in lots of problems
that I haven't written on here.
So we've talked about supervised
learning,
and that's where we're going to
live for most of the semester.
But at the very end of the
semester, we're going to touch
on unsupervised learning.
Now if supervised learning is
about predicting y from x,
and we have a right answer,
what do you think unsupervised
learning is?
Yes, and write it in your name?
Okay.
It's like you don't have a right
answer.
Yeah, so what are you trying to
do instead?
Maybe do something and not have
anything to match it with.
You're on the right track.
The idea,
exactly, is that we don't have a
right answer.
What that means is our goal
isn't actually to predict
anything.
Instead, it's to find structure
within the data we have.
Let me give you two examples of
what this type of problem may
look like.
So I wrote these course notes
last summer When the show The
Summer I Turned Pretty was
popular,
and that's what we were watching
at home and Grey's Anatomy
Popular, so these are the shows
we were watching at home.
So these are the examples I used
Pretend I run Netflix or Hulu
There's no streaming service
that has both of these shows on
but pretend one of them did and
for each of my users
I kept track of how much they
like each of the shows they're
watching
Okay,
so I have some hypothetical
group of say nine users here and
for each one I know how much
they liked The Samurai Turned
Pretty and how much they liked
Grey's Anatomy.
Now that's all I have.
I just have these ratings.
But if I plot this out,
what does- what are you seeing
here?
What are you seeing?
Yes, and- Greetings?
Connor.
It kind of goes in a little
squiggle, so like if you like
The Samurai Turned Pretty you
don't necessarily like Grey's
Anatomy as much or you also
really like it or you like both
of them kind of like a fair
amount.
Yeah,
it seems like, and I think this
may be what you were getting at,
it seems like roughly the users,
even though we didn't already
have them placed into groups,
all they did was just make a
Netflix account and watch shows,
it seems like they naturally
fall into some of these groups.
These groups are called
clusters.
And clustering is an example
of an unsupervised learning
problem, where you have a bunch
of data points in high
dimensions.
And your job is to place them
into groups where users or data
points in each group are similar
to one another and different
from the other groups.
Why might you want to do this?
Again, pretend you're running
the streaming service And you
have a bunch of users,
and you place them into groups.
Why might you want to do that?
Yeah, and what was your name?
Alessandra.
You could recommend them shows
based off the cluster.
Exactly.
What you could do is recommend
all of the users in a cluster
the same types of shows.
So if these two users,
the ones at 8, 3 and 10, 4,
if they both like some new show,
what were we watching yesterday,
One Tree Hill.
If they both like One Tree Hill,
well,
then maybe this person will also
like that, because they all have
similar tastes.
But maybe people in other
clusters,
I don't have enough information
to recommend them One Tree Hill
as well,
because we don't know that they
like the same things that the
people in the bottom right
cluster like.
And so now when you go on a
streaming service, Netflix,
Hulu, whatever,
you see how they start to come
up with recommendations for you.
So that's one example of an
unsupervised learning problem.
Now, in practice,
figuring out what the groups are
is much more difficult than just
eyeballing it.
Why is that?
Well, it's because these
streaming services don't just
keep track of how much you like
two different shows.
They keep track of how much you
like every show you've watched,
and that may be hundreds.
And you factor in all the movies
as well.
So instead of being able to draw
a graph in two dimensions,
we're thinking in tens or
hundreds of dimensions.
Okay, and then the question is,
how do we still place users into
groups when we have so many
pieces of information for each
one and we can't just eyeball
the groups ourselves?
That's the kind of problem
machine learning will solve,
and this sort of thinking of
data points in high dimensions,
dimensions higher than 2D and
3D, is the type of skill
that we're going to develop in
this class.
One other example of a machine
learning problem, and I want
to see if I can get this to work
here, because if we can, it'll
be really cool.
Let's test this out here.
Okay.
I don't think it's going to
work.
Let me show you it in the notes
and then tell you what I was
going to do.
Another example of a machine
learning problem is one of
dimensionality reduction.
What does this mean?
And I'll show you the picture I
wanted to show you in the notes.
Let's go back to that example
down
here or just work with us for a
second.
And we just said in this
hypothetical streaming service,
we have scores for the various
shows that a user has watched.
And if there are lots of shows
that each user has watched,
then it's impossible to
visualize all of the data at
once.
Because if you want one axis per
show,
well then if they've watched any
more than three shows,
we can't visualize this data.
Dimensionality reduction is a
tool for taking high-dimensional
data
and turning it into a
lower-dimensional representation
that we can visualize in two or
three dimensions.
So imagine I have a table in
which there are n rows,
one per user,
and d columns,
one per show.
And just as an example,
let's just say we have a
thousand columns.
So for example, this first
column could be the summer I
turn pretty column.
The next could be the Grey's
Anatomy column.
The next could be the One Tree
Hill column, and so on and so
forth.
You can't visualize this data.
But through dimensionality
reduction techniques,
what you can produce
is a smaller dataset
with still one row per user,
because you want to keep the
information you have for every
user,
but instead of needing 1,000
pieces of information for each
user,
you can summarize or reduce that
information into just two or
three pieces of information per
user.
Now, the naive way to do that
would be to just pick the shows
that you thought were most
important.
And you could do that.
But there's actually an even
more informative way of doing
that, which involves creating
new sort of hypothetical TV
shows that you create using a
combination of each of the
original TV shows.
And when you create these new
hypothetical TV shows,
you do that in a way that sort
of keeps and retains as
much of the variance between
users as possible.
And so these new columns I might
call new feature
one
and new feature two.
OK, let me see if the other
example I wanted to get working
here is going to work.
I fear it is not.
OK.
Well, that's that.
I'll show you what it was going
to be.
This was an application of
linear algebra that's related to
this idea of dimensionality
reduction.
And it's like one of the final
things we're going to do this
semester.
Here's a picture of my dog,
Junior.
It's the same picture you saw on
the slides.
What we will learn to do is
think of an image as a matrix.
You can think of it as a table
with rows and columns.
And each pixel in the image,
in this example, this image is
grayscale.
We can just represent each pixel
with just a number from 0 to
255.
That's a standard way that
colors are represented.
0 means the pixel is dark or
black here, and 255 would mean
that it's white.
To store this image,
I believe it's a 300 by 400
image, so 300 pixels wide, 400
pixels tall,
I would need to store 1.2
million numbers,
like the pixel amount at each of
these 400 by 300 pixels.
Linear algebra is going to give
us a way to compress the image
optimally.
And so what you're seeing here,
and if you go to chapter 10.2
in the notes, you'll see a
slider for this.
What we've visualized is what's
called a rank k approximation of
the image.
And you can think of, for now,
the rank of the matrix as being
the amount of information in it.
And right now, the slider is at
k is equal to 1.
And what do you notice about
this low rank approximation of
the image?
It's not a dog,
it's not really much of
anything.
And what you should actually
notice here is that every column
of this image is really just the
same column, some are brighter
than others.
But there's really only one
pattern, you see this like big
cross here.
But as I add to the value of K,
you can see slowly the picture
of Junior starts to get
reproduced,
okay? And in order to reproduce
the full picture,
you would need the full rank of
the matrix, which here would be
likely 300.
But what we're seeing is that at
rank 30, if you squint, it does
still look like junior.
And it turns out you can store
these low rank
approximations very efficiently
using linear algebra.
So this is the type of thing
that we are going to learn about
this semester.
Now, what was I going to do?
What I was going to do is take a
selfie with everyone here in the
class and use that picture to do
the same low-rank approximation,
but my notebook was crashing.
You can see I tested this out
yesterday with just a selfie on
my laptop,
and we were going to put a
picture of us in here.
But that didn't work, but that's
OK.
Anyways,
those are all examples of
problems
in the world of machine
learning.
That low-rank approximation one
is not one in which we were
trying to predict a right
answer, but there we were trying
to retain structure as best as
we could.
Do we have a sense of the types
of problems that fall in the
machine learning umbrella?
This is not a comprehensive
list.
For some reason,
projector is disconnected here.
This is not a comprehensive
list.
The third branch that was on the
slide here that I didn't talk
much about is called
reinforcement learning, and you
may hear about this a lot in the
media.
Does anyone know what
reinforcement learning is about?
Yeah, through.
Basically,
it's like a reward function.
And so you allow the model to
interact with whatever you're
having to do.
And then it learns over time
itself
by getting the reward when it
doesn't do that.
Exactly.
The main idea behind
reinforcement learning
is less about predicting y from
x.
And instead, what it does is it
simulates a bot or an agent in
an environment.
And it gives it rewards for
doing the right thing.
And it penalizes it for doing
the wrong thing.
And the right and wrong thing is
customized by whoever sets up
the agent.
And you get it to learn using
positive reinforcement, sort of
modeled by how children are
given good things when they
behave well and punished,
hopefully not too poorly,
when they don't behave well.
And you hear about reinforcement
learning a lot in the media,
especially in the context of
these coding agents and the
latest versions of Chat, GPT,
and Claude,
because they actually use all
parts of this machine learning
taxonomy to build these systems.
And you can read more about this
in chapter 1.1.
But the hot new stage of the
training of these machine
learning systems is this
reinforcement learning step,
where the model has learned from
all of its training data.
And as a final step before the
model is shipped to your chat
GPT and cloud apps,
what they do
is they train it to give
responses that it thinks the
users will like.
Okay,
so for example in the context of
Claude code or chat GPT codex
What they do at that final stage
is they reinforcement learn the
models to incentivize them to
write code.
Well
but what that means is if you
use Claude code and The like
other models that are
specifically meant for code if
you ask them to like write an
essay for you It sounds cryptic
It doesn't sound as good as if
you just went to the regular
clotted chat GPT And I thought
it's because these coding models
are incentivized at the final
step to write code, which can
degrade its performance in
writing regular English, for
example.
So these systems that you hear
about all the time, they use all
stages of this process.
And we are going to start over
here in regression, which is
under supervised learning.
But I want you to be
conversationally fluent with
these other branches of machine
learning.
Sound good?
Okay,
but this is not a class that is
on machine learning directly,
instead it's called math for
machine learning.
Okay,
and so what are we actually
gonna learn?
What I've done here is I have
put a screenshot of the table of
contents
of our course notes.
And what I'm doing right now is
just annotating what sections of
the notes are covered in
midterms one, two, and then
post-midterm, too.
What I've tried to do is I've
set this course up so that
you're never,
or not never,
but there are not many times
where you're left wondering what
is the point of the math.
What I want to do is start today
with a problem that is motivated
from supervised learning.
There's something that we want
to learn how to predict.
And what we are going to do is
introduce the relevant
mathematical tools that we need
so that we can learn how to make
better predictions.
That's going to be the running
theme this semester.
I already said what it is,
we're going to learn how to
predict how long it's going to
take for us to get to work,
using someone's real dataset
where they log their commute
times.
We're going to start with that,
introduce some mathematical
tools, and for the first few
weeks we're not going to talk
about linear algebra at all,
because you can actually get
surprisingly far without needing
to know what a vector is.
But there will come a point in
our story where we can't
actually progress until we know
about linear algebra, and that's
why from chapters three to six
of the course notes,
we're going to just take a
little detour from the main
story line and introduce all of
these linear algebra ideas, but
there's a purpose for it all, so
that we can return to the linear
regression story, or the
regression story,
and solve it more deeply and
thoroughly using our linear
algebra tools.
That's what we do in chapter
seven.
And then once we've covered
that,
we think of other possible ways
of solving the same types of
problems, which will allow us to
introduce other aspects of
linear algebra and also
multivariate calculus, which you
will see as a theme throughout
the course.
So at any point in the semester,
if it seems like we're just
doing a bunch of random math,
don't hesitate to ask, OK, how
does this connect to the broader
storyline? Now, admittedly, in
some places, it'll seem like
we're doing something that is
very disconnected from the
broader storyline, and part of
that is true because this class
has to satisfy the linear
algebra prerequisite,
and I think it would be
dishonest to leave out big parts
of linear algebra just because
someone might now think they're
relevant to machine learning.
I still want you to learn it
all,
but I'm trying to do my best to
make sure you know why we are
learning it all.
OK, so you're not losing
anything
by taking this class versus
other linear algebra options.
Sound OK?
All right.
OK,
so now I want to talk a little
bit about how the course works
logistically.
Has everyone seen the course
website, ex245.org?
Yeah?
OK, question?
OK, cool.
So a couple of things to note.
We are not going to use Canvas
for anything.
I haven't activated it.
Everything you need is going to
be linked from the course
website.
I just want to make sure to
touch on a few of the key points
here.
And everything I'm about to say
is in the syllabus, but there
are lots of things in the
syllabus that I'm not going to
say here.
So make sure to revisit it for
all of the details.
First, lectures.
Here's the main thing that is
new this semester.
Lecture attendance is part of
your grade.
This is the first time I've ever
done this.
This is my sixth year teaching.
I've never required lecture
attendance.
But like I said at the start,
I think it's becoming a little
too easy to just not show up,
show up just for exams, and sort
of be a number at this school.
What I want you to do is, like I
said, is take advantage of the
fact that there are plenty of
other brilliant students with
you,
that you have TAs and
instructors,
and people who really care about
your experience in the class,
and that's sort of why lecture
attendance is encouraged.
Now, it's not strictly
mandatory,
okay? So it's 5% of your grade.
But if you'd rather not come to
lecture,
that extra 5% can go towards
your final exam instead, if you
would like.
But then that would mean exams
are worth 75% of your grade,
which is pretty substantial.
So lecture attendance is
encouraged.
We will take attendance every
week.
I'll do that in just a little
bit.
But that 5% goes to the max of
your attendance grade and your
final exam grade.
Sound OK?
All right.
And I'll try my best to keep
lectures engaging.
Today, there's a lot of me
talking.
But in most cases, you will
spend a lot of your time
actually working things out on
pencil paper.
I'll walk around and see how
things are going.
And we will take up your
solutions, OK? So come prepared
to write,
ask questions.
I don't want this to just be me
talking at you for 80 minutes,
OK?
And also, one thing that I want
you to hold me accountable for,
because I always say I'll do
this, but I don't, is I want to
make sure we take like a three
or four minute break at least in
the middle of every lecture
sometimes I'll just talk for 80
minutes so if it seems like we
were supposed to have a break
but didn't I know it's probably
hard to say like hey you said we
would have a break but like I
don't know say something
passive-aggressive I'll get the
hint and we'll have a break okay
so lectures they're recorded
recordings will be linked
directly on the course homepage
so if you go to eeks245.org
right now under lecture one
right now all that is there are
the readings but in like an hour
I'll post the stuff that I'm
writing on my iPad will be
linked there and then in maybe
two hours the recording link
will be there too so that's the
only place you need to look.
Speaking of the readings those
are the primary source of
information in this class
they're not it's not a textbook
that we found somewhere else I
wrote it personally and it's
like designed to follow the
specific story that I just told
you about okay.
Now unlike other classes where
there is a textbook but like no
one really cares,
that's not how it works here.
And to show you that that's not
how it works,
if you go to the
advice to the student tab in the
top left,
what you can see are unedited
comments from students who took
the class in fall 25.
They all said the same thing in
winter 26 and spring 26, so I
haven't updated this.
But the key piece of advice that
I think they're leaving for you
is that the course notes are
your friend here.
What I'm gonna try and do is use
the same numbers and same
examples and same story that is
in the notes But the notes have
far more detail than we will be
able to discuss in lecture And
that's because the notes are
designed for you to refer to
them when you're in lab and when
you're in homework
Okay, I'm not expecting that you
read them before coming to class
Okay But many students find it
useful to skim them before
coming to class and they're
already linked on the course
homepage for the whole semester,
so you can read them before
coming to class.
You can have them open if you'd
like.
Do whatever is best for you.
But just somewhere in your
regular study strategy, reading
the notes must be part of it.
And there are lots of examples
in there,
and I've tried to add some
videos in there as well, of
questions that are solved that I
think if you solve those
questions yourself,
it'll help when it comes to
doing the homeworks and exams.
So don't treat them as optional.
They should be sort of like a
regular thing.
If you're not regularly looking
at the course notes, then
something is probably wrong with
your study strategy.
If you find any typos or issues
or things that are confusing, or
you read something and it still
doesn't make sense and then you
asked Claude and it made more
sense,
if you ever encounter a
situation like that, please tell
me.
I want to make them as clear as
possible.
And it's very likely that there
are parts in here that are more
confusing than they need to be.
So if you ever read something
and it doesn't make sense,
and someone else, human or not,
explains it better,
tell me and we will update the
notes.
Okay, it's all hosted on github.
If you just click this github
button, you can even see the
github source for it You can
make a pull request if you want,
okay
All right
So those are lectures
Labs are the next essential
component of the course.
Those are also a part of your
grade worth 10% Everyone's in an
assigned lab section though.
You can attend a different lab
if you need to
They're all in Wednesdays and
the way that labs will work is
that you show up and we will
give you a physical worksheet
Okay, and that worksheet isn't
posted on the website ahead of
time, because we really want to
encourage you to practice this
act of writing math on paper,
because ultimately your exams,
which are worth 70-75% of your
grade, are also just written on
paper.
So we use the same format as the
exams for the lab, same
headings, same boxes, it all,
a lab sort of looks like a mini
exam.
Okay, and the point of the lab
worksheet is to reinforce the
ideas from the Tuesday before
and the Thursday before okay and
sometimes preview things for the
next Thursday okay and so the
TAs will be there they will take
up solutions to the questions
that people find tricky and they
will be there as a resource to
help with the questions you may
have with the lab okay or
content in general all right and
you should think of labs as
being like the first place you
go to get practice so the
homeworks will usually be harder
than the labs.
So the main workflow is come to
lecture, read the notes,
work on some of the activities
in the notes,
go to lab, build that
foundational understanding, and
then the homeworks will push it
a little further.
Homeworks are worth 15% of your
grade, and this is where I think
much of the learning will come.
One new thing that I'm also
trying this semester is that
you're actually not allowed to
type up the solutions.
In previous semesters,
like in some other classes, I
would provide an overleaf
template for LaTeX for students
to type up their solutions, but
it just became way too tempting
to just give that to chatgpt and
say, put my solutions here.
And this way,
if you're going to cheat
yourself,
well at least you still have to
write it out yourself on paper,
and maybe some learning will
still happen.
But you can tell the grading
scheme is set up such that
there's not really much of an
advantage to doing that.
Suppose you cheat your way
through every homework,
that still only gets you 15% of
your grade.
70% of it is coming from exams,
which require you to work on
everything sort of in-person
live, no assistance.
And so doing the homeworks
yourself and struggling through
them,
and coming to us for help, of
course,
when you are struggling, is how
you will learn.
Yes, question.
And your name was Allison,
right?
Yeah.
So homeworks have to be
handwritten?
Or you can also write them on a
tablet and upload them.
Yeah, that's totally fine.
Yeah.
You just can't type them in any
way.
But writing them on a tablet is
fine.
OK.
I'm not trying to scare you into
like,
that's not the vibe I want to go
for.
I'm just trying to say,
I really want you to work on the
material earnestly and come to
us for help.
A thing you may have noticed in
some of your other classes over
this past year is that office
hours attendance is way lower
than, well,
I guess it depends on how long
you've been at the university.
But overall,
office hours attendance is way
lower than it has been in the
past.
When you took 280 and 281 last
year,
before I got to Michigan, and
when I was interviewing here a
couple of years ago,
people would say office hours
queues for 280 on the Euchre Day
would be like three hours long,
and now the 280 TAs and
instructors tell me nobody's in
office hours on the day.
We know why that is,
but again,
I'm not saying you can't use any
AI tools at all.
That's not my vibe at all.
OK, there's a utility to them.
But you don't want to use them
to circumvent the productive
struggle of working on questions
that you don't know how to do
and trying to figure them out.
A good analogy that I have at
the back of my mind is like,
if you're training to run a
marathon,
driving 26 miles, I guess it
technically accomplishes the act
of getting you from point A to
point B in the same distance
that a marathon is in.
But it doesn't help you train
for the marathon at all.
Right or similarly like there's
a reason people go to the gym
and lift weights when forklifts
exist It's not just to lift the
weight, right? it's the act of
doing it that builds something
in you and it's the act of
working on the homeworks and
Trying to figure out answers to
questions that you don't already
know
That forms connections in your
brain
Okay, and we're here to help
throughout that entire process.
Okay, please take advantage of
our office hours Please post on
ed.
We really want to help you
succeed in this class
OK, any questions with
logistically how the class is
going to work?
Yes.
And remind me of your name?
Emma.
I know you said it's what works
best for you in terms of reading
the notes before or after the
lecture.
I was just wondering if in
previous semesters,
the majority of people found it
better to do one or the other,
but it was truly just a mixed
bag.
From what I can tell, it was a
mixed bag.
I'll say that the first time I
taught this class last fall,
people didn't really have the
option of reading it because I'd
only write them like the day of,
more or less.
Now they're all posted.
And so I think I'll try and
survey.
We have the welcome survey that
you should fill out, but we will
have several similar surveys
throughout the semester.
I'll try and get a sense of what
people here are doing so that I
can have better guidance for the
future.
But as far as I know, it's a
pretty mixed bag.
What I do know is that when I
walk around and lecture or when
I have in the past,
I would commonly see people
having the notes open.
And any time students would come
to office hours to work on
homeworks, they would also have
the notes open.
Okay,
any other questions?
I guess the last thing I'll say
is that we have three exams,
so two midterms and a final.
The dates are all on the course
website.
One perhaps unique setup with
our final exam is that it is
cumulative, but if you do better
on the final exam questions that
are about midterm one topics,
will increase your midterm one
grade.
So the final exam, you can think
of it as being broken into three
sections.
midterm one questions, midterm
two questions, and final exam
questions, or post midterm two
questions.
They're not, of course, going to
be the same questions.
It'll just be about the same
content.
Suppose you get a 50 on the
original midterm one,
and you get a 90 on the midterm
one questions that are on the
final exam, again, about those
topics, but not the same
questions,
will increase your midterm one
grade from a 50 to the average
of those two, which is a 70.
Okay?
So it's sort of incentive at the
end of the semester to go back
and review things that were
earlier.
Okay?
Now, Midterm 2 is not
technically cumulative in that I
wouldn't ask a question that
could have been on Midterm 1,
but the topics in the course do
build on each other.
So it'll be hard to go into
Midterm 2 without knowing the
things in Midterm 1.
But that policy that I just
stated is called the redemption
policy and it's outlined in the
syllabus, and usually about half
the class benefits from them.
OK, question and yes.
What was your name again?
Boyan.
I have a question about the
policy.
Does it work the opposite way?
No, no.
So if you do worse,
if we reverse those numbers and
you got a 90 on midterm one,
50 on the midterm one questions
on the final exam, we just keep
your 90.
So this can only help you.
OK.
Other questions with how the
course works?
Again, make sure to read the
syllabus in depth.
that talks about the slip days
you have for homeworks,
the drops you have for labs and
homeworks, and the attendance
policy, all of those things.
Sound good?
OK,
let's test out the attendance
mechanism before we get into
some content.
What we are going to use is this
website,
Poll Everywhere.
I'm going to write the link up
here.
And starting now,
you should be able to submit.
And so if you go here, every
lecture,
I'll have a slightly new form
there.
And what it will have is a box
that just asks,
what is the most confusing thing
we've done so far?
So if you have questions about
the policy or any field
of machine learning, here's a
place you can enter it.
Now, one thing I'll note is that
this requires you to log in with
your U of M email.
So I already pre-registered
everyone in this class to the
site.
If you try and log in with your
U of M email and it doesn't
work,
let me know and that may be
because you just enrolled
in the last 48 hours or so and I
can add you in manually.
And the link for this is also in
the
toolbar on the course website.
If you click the attendance
button, it should work.
I'll give us a few minutes and
this will also count as our
break.
Let's see here.
Oh,
did it still say that? How about
try this? Yeah, okay,
sorry,
thank you.
It's 11.25,
we'll start again at 11.26,
so just make sure to log in.
Yeah,
that's okay.
Okay,
I'll take it to Jim, yes, you're
right.
Excuse me.
You're supposed to take a right,
and Trump's gonna go out.
Oh.
Yeah.
Does that mean that Alex didn't
have anything to do with me this
time? Yes, sir.
Yeah, I just had two lefties
today, so.
Oh,
I was going to ask you a
question.
Sorry, I just asked you a
It's clear.
There's some on there.
There's some.
It was three.
It's very difficult.
We're going to play a couple of
games.
Any of you guys see?
Probably you should go around.
It's a California game.
Two more stops now, if you
realize.
They didn't turn on the ground.
Well, you might.
I think it helps.
It's pretty good.
Okay,
as everyone...
Everyone checked in?
All right.
Let me just double check that I
have everything here.
Okay.
Says I have 64 responses.
I think we have slightly more,
we have more more than 64 people
in the class and more than 64
people here.
So if you didn't get a chance to
check in just come check with me
afterwards okay I want to start
our actual content here and this
is going to follow chapter 1.2
in the course notes we will
start our like main course
storyline now and we will pick
this up on Thursday here's a
real data set
that someone collected by
logging information about their
daily commute it's a real person
if you look at the course notes
like the github repository I
found this on actually I found
that someone posted this on
LinkedIn three years ago.
And I was like,
one day I could use this for a
class,
and wrote it down, and so
LinkedIn is useful for
something, I guess.
This person lives in the Seattle
area and commuted to work every
day and wrote down,
among other things,
what date it was,
the day of the week,
the time they left in the
morning,
and how long the commute
actually took.
I actually live in Detroit and
commute here, so I guess I could
have made my own data set over
this past year.
But we'll use this guy's data
set.
In the context of the taxonomy
of machine learning that we
looked at before,
minutes here,
that's our y variable.
That is our target that we want
to predict.
And so now the question is,
among the other columns in the
data set we were provided,
what should we use to try and
make those predictions?
Well, the most natural thing to
use,
I think at least when we're
starting,
is the time we leave in the
morning.
To validate that assumption, it
would help if we looked at the
relationship between departure
hour, or time we leave in the
morning, commute time and we
will do that in the next slide
and what we see is that indeed
it seems like there is some
pattern between the time we
leave in the morning and how
long the commute actually takes
so it seems like a reasonable
choice to try and use departure
time as one of the inputs
into this particular prediction
model.
One thing I want to comment on
is how All of these departure
times are stored.
10.816667.
What do you think that means?
It's just 10 hours and then 8.6
of an hour.
Remind me of an email server
with an A.
A mark.
A mark, right.
OK.
Exactly.
What this is saying is that this
is 10 AM plus 81% of an hour.
So this is going to be like 1044
or something like that.
This way you don't have to store
the times as weird strings and
then you have to parse where the
colon is and figure out if it's
am or pm.
Instead they are just stored as
floating point numbers that we
can do math with.
It also seems like it could be
useful to use what day of the
week it is.
Right, like maybe it takes
longer to get to work on Mondays
and Fridays when there's more
traffic.
It seems like a natural thing to
want to try and do,
but what is the issue when it
comes to using days of the week?
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Madge, it'll be like 3D.
Sorry, could you please repeat
that?
It'll be like 3D with three
dimensions.
Yeah, one issue is that the
graph itself with all in that
visualizes the day, the
departure hour, and the commute
time would be in 3D, but that's
something we can overcome.
There's another possible issue.
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Brian.
It's like a compounding
variable,
like the departure time is not
the same,
you can't like find it to the
specific day.
I see what you're getting at,
though we can build a model that
allows us to use any day and any
departure hour as inputs.
So that alone is not directly an
issue.
And in general, when you have a
really big complicated dataset,
there will be features that are
related to other features.
And that's just something you
sort of have to deal with.
Any other ideas? Yes.
And what was your name again?
Musab.
It's categorical.
It's categorical,
right?
Exactly,
and what we're going to try and
do is come up with some formula,
some mathematical formula that
takes in the departure hour,
does some calculation to it, and
spits out a predicted commute
time.
But what is that formula going
to do with the day of the week?
Because that's not a number.
That's something we're gonna
have to address.
And it is something we will
address later on in the semester
using a technique called one-hot
encoding, which is how we are
gonna turn these words into
numbers.
Okay,
for now, let's just focus on
predicting commute time using
departure time,
okay? So the commute time is
going to be our y, and the
departure time is going to be
our x.
So here's a graph of y versus x.
Commute time on the y-axis,
the time we left in the morning
on the x-axis.
Each one of these data points,
let's use a different color
here,
is something like x subscripted
number comma y subscripted
number.
And that number five just tells
us which row of the data set we
pulled this point from.
So in this hypothetical,
this was the fifth point in our
data set.
Sound good?
So we're going to see a lot of
subscripts moving forward.
Now, our goal,
like I said,
is to predict commute
times.
But it's not really just to
predict commute times in the
data set we already have.
For all of the historical data,
we already know how long it took
to get to work.
What is our real goal? What is
the point of doing this?
Yeah, Emma?
To know that, like,
on any given day,
whatever time you leave,
like a data that's not in there.
Exactly, the point is to be able
to use this technique
to predict how long tomorrow's
commute is going to take,
or next Tuesday's commute is
going to take.
But I want to use it when I
don't already know the right
answer.
And so if all I was trying to do
is make good predictions for
this data set,
here's a function that could do
that.
Why is this bad?
It is what we call overfit to
the training data.
And the reason that that's bad
is that it has clearly gone
beyond the general trend in the
relationship between commute
time and departure time, and it
has all of these little wiggles
and bumps which are unlikely to
represent a broader trend.
And so what this means is if I
go and try and use this orange
curve to predict how long
tomorrow's commute is going to
take and how I would use it is
go to wherever I plan on leaving
in the morning on the x-axis and
look at the height of this graph
on the y-axis.
This would do a worse job than
far simpler models would,
because this has way too many
squiggles that don't represent a
general trend.
They just represent the specific
traffic on any one day or the
fact that I stopped at Starbucks
coming home or something like
that.
And so keep this at the back of
your mind.
Our goal is to build models that
generalize well to unseen data.
Now with that,
I've used the word model,
but I haven't actually defined
what I mean by a model.
A model,
you know, people use this word a
lot and you say, okay,
chat jibbity the new 5.6
model or whatever,
right? One unifying term that
defines all types of models,
statistical,
large language model, machine
learning,
is that a model is a set of
assumptions
about how data was generated,
or equivalently,
how the world works.
If you think philosophically for
a moment any model you've heard
of is just an assumption about
how one specific part of the
world works.
Now there's a famous quote that
you may have heard of in like a
high school statistics or
science class which is that all
models are wrong but some are
useful.
Has anyone heard this before?
A few people.
What is the essence of that
statement?
All models are wrong, but some
are useful.
Like, what does that mean?
Yeah.
And remind us of your name?
Zara.
Maybe it's like,
not every model can be right all
the time.
Exactly.
What this is saying is that no
matter how hard you try,
models will make mistakes.
They won't reflect every single
part of how the world works.
And we see that even now when we
have these billion or trillion
dollar models released by the
big AI companies that still
don't answer everything
correctly.
And so one interpretation of
this,
and I'm sorry,
all models are wrong, but some
are useful.
What does that mean?
Well, it means that even simple
models
can explain useful things about
how the world works.
The example I like using for
this is the fact you learned in
high school science or physics,
which is that acceleration due
to gravity is 9.81
meters per second squared.
Do we remember this fact?
It's not always true,
right? If you drop, I don't
know, if I drop a piece of
paper, that's not the speed at
which it's going to accelerate,
right? There are other variables
that affect this.
It affects, you know, things
like how far you are from the
equator and what the drag
coefficient of the thing you
dropped is.
Still, that simple model is
useful enough for us to be able
to do calculations,
okay? And so what I'm getting at
here is that even the most
complicated models will be
wrong.
And so there actually is some
utility in studying simpler
models.
And so what we are going to do
in this class
is actually start
with models that seem overly
simplistic.
When you look at this,
what was the first type of model
that you assumed we would draw
on here,
knowing nothing else.
Yeah,
Paul? Like linear regression?
Yeah, what you saw here is maybe
something you saw in a high
school statistics class,
something like a line of best
fit
that we could use to predict
commute time given departure
time.
And indeed, this is a valid
model, and it's one that we will
study.
Here, we will call that the
simple linear
regression model.
Simple just means that it only
has one input variable.
And again, input variables are
what we call features.
Here, our only feature is
departure time.
So yes, this is a model we will
study.
But I'm actually going to start
even simpler than that.
What model could be simpler than
this?
How could we be even more basic?
Yes, and remind us of your name?
I'm Alex.
Alex.
You have a constant model? A
constant model, good.
Here, this model returns
different predictions depending
the time we leave in the
morning.
What if I say, no, that's too
complicated?
why don't I instead just always
predict the same commute time?
Sounds basic,
and indeed the simple linear
regression model here is better
in almost every way.
It'll also generalize just as
well, but the constant model is
not totally useless because
imagine you had a conversation
with someone about, you know,
you have this historical data
about your commutes and they
ask,
okay how long does it usually
take for you to get to work,
you're probably not going to
give them a complicated formula.
You'll give them a one-number
summary.
And that's really just the
constant model.
And so here's the philosophy
we're going to use here.
I want to start with the
constant model.
So today,
Thursday,
next Tuesday, we're mostly just
going to talk about the constant
model.
But I'm going to use it to
introduce a lot of notation
formulas and machinery that we
will use throughout our machine
learning journey.
So we're going to start with a
simple model,
develop what I call the
three-step modeling recipe,
and then throughout the
semester, look at more and more
complicated models through that
same recipe.
So we'll start basic and then
increase our complexity from
there.
Now, let's introduce a tiny bit
of notation here.
A hypothesis function
is a
function which I'll denote with
the letter H takes in features
and returns predicted
Y values.
So, a hypothesis function is
what you use to make your
predictions, and ultimately what
we are trying to do here is find
good hypothesis functions,
or build a useful
hypothesis function.
The idea is that each model,
or each model type,
so for example constant or
simple linear regression
has its own
hypothesis class format.
So let me
start with the constant model.
The constant model is always
of the form h of xi equals some
constant.
I'll call it W.
And what I'm seeing on the
right, I'll zoom in a little
because I know this is small,
is for three different values of
W,
60,
70, and 100,
what the resulting constant
model looks like on our data
set.
Now, what you should see is that
some choices of w are better
than others.
Like, choosing w equals 100
seems a little nonsensical for
this data set, because none of
the data,
like very few of our commutes
were in the range of 100
minutes.
W equals 60 also seems to be a
little low,
but the question is where do we
put it in the middle?
Like 70 seems good.
Do we agree that W equals 70
seems the best of these choices?
Yeah,
but maybe 71 is better, and
maybe 70.37
is even better than that.
How do we know?
Okay, and that is the big
problem we are going to study on
Thursday.
how do we figure out what to
make W?
W is what is called a parameter.
A parameter is an aspect of a
model that we have to pick.
So different parameters will
lead into different predictions.
And w is always the letter we
will use for parameters.
The constant model has just one
parameter.
Yes? What is a parameter
different from a feature?
A feature is the input variable.
So like,
here, let me give you an example
of the simple linear regression
model.
And I think that'll make it a
little more clear.
We'll come back to the constant
model in a second.
And the simple linear regression
model,
various versions of it look like
this.
How many parameters do you think
it has?
the simple linear regression
model has? Yes, and remind us of
your name.
Oh,
sorry.
Yeah,
I'll admit it, but yeah.
Sam.
Sam, yeah.
Two.
And what are, OK, what are those
parameters?
Slope and the wider set.
Good.
And what was your name?
Chinmay.
Chinmay, awesome.
Good.
The simple linear regression
model has two parameters,
two things we can tweak about
the model.
The X's,
those are the features.
Orange is a bad color for that.
I'll just use blue here.
So remember, before I said the
X's represent the commute,
sorry, the departure times, and
the y's represent the commute
times.
So xi, you should think of that
as like 8.30
AM or 9.45
AM.
The parameters are what we are
using
to help us make the prediction.
And in this case, what we do is
we take the intercept parameter,
w0,
add that to the slope parameter
multiplied by the feature.
So is that distinction clear?
OK,
good question, because that's an
important thing to clarify.
So the parameters are these w's
that we about the model,
the X's are the input
information that we have from
raw data.
Are we clear on the difference
between a parameter and a
feature?
And we will cover this again on
Thursday because I want to make
sure the notation is clear.
Now this definition of a
parameter is the same as the
definition of a parameter you
hear about in large language
models.
But this model just has two
parameters.
The latest, Chachipiti and
Clods, have hundreds of billions
of parameters.
And so they can perform more
sophisticated calculations and
be used to predict more
complicated things than just the
commute time tomorrow.
But it's the same essence.
And to train those models, all
they are doing is figuring out
what the best w's to use are.
It's the same principle that we
are using here.
OK?
Here, for the simple linear
regression model,
I've shown three different sets
of parameters.
In the first I used an intercept
of 160 and a slope of negative
10,
then I used an intercept of 20
and a slope of 5, and in the
third I used an intercept of 100
and a slope of negative 3.
And we see that some of these
choices are better than others.
The first combination of
intercept and slope seems to be
the best.
The middle one seems to make no
sense at all.
And the last one seems to be OK,
but worse than the first.
We agree?
OK, so the question is,
what is the optimal or best
combination of parameters?
It's the same question that I
posed with the constant model.
We have the model drawn for
three different choices of the
one parameter,
W.
For the are you drawing this
flat line,
right? The constant model
doesn't have a slope.
So the question is,
what is the best w?
Now, do you have some guesses?
In the context of the constant
model,
do you have guesses for what the
best w could be?
The best constant to predict?
Yes, and remind us of your name?
Caitlin.
Is it like where you're the
closest to most amount data
points you know? Yeah, it feels
like the best W would be one
that seems to be like in the
middle of the data somehow
But there are lots of ways we
could formulate that like do we
mean the median of the data?
Do we mean halfway between the
min and the max?
Do we mean the average?
Do we mean the 60th percentile?
Those are all possible answers.
And so what we're gonna do when
we come back on Thursday is come
up with a way of measuring
Which of those candidate choices
of W is the one best one?
Okay, and so when you go to lab
tomorrow, you're going to review
some of the core ideas
in calculus that we need to
answer that question because it
is a calculus question.
Okay, that's it.
Like I said, these iPad notes
will be posted on the website
after class and so will the
recording.
And I have office hours after
this.
I will always have office hours
after lecture in my office,
which is on the fourth floor of
the BBB building.
And you can just come by and say
hi, and if there are enough of
us, we can just go Go to the
patio and chill for a bit.
I'm senior.
I'm junior.
Junior.
What's your name?
I just know for a lot of
festivals.
Although, I'm lucky.
I'm not gonna be at May's best
festival though because human
festivals aren't at the same
time.
Good to see you again.
We'll review it all.
Review it all in the course
notes tab so we can review it as
well.
We have one lecture,
so I mean, it seems fun.
That's all for you.
If you submit it, I'll help you
out.
Thank you.
Yeah, no worries.
It's like this stuff.
OK, I'm sitting in the middle of
class.
I'm kind of like in the middle,
so I toward in.
Are you excited?
Yeah, I'd say so.
It's the most excited member of
the class.
I don't know if they're funny or
not.
But your name and your U of M,
you know?
I think that's useful,
but you don't have to write down
every single thing I say because
it's all posted anyway.
It's just like write down the
key things you think you'll need
to remember in the discussion.
Take care of you as well.
I don't know,
it just fell out of the box.
Oh, I have a question for you.
Um,
the homework one is kind of...
Will the topics covered be about
that was meant to be learned or
will it be the previous one? It
will usually be about the
previous one.
So,
the homework one
is more just about prereq stuff.
Uh,
homework two will be the first
homework that's about to step
up.
Thank you.
Is that the score?
No, I also assume that everybody
I meet in these classes are
going to be computer science,
too.
No,
I want to do user experience
design.
But I was already cockside, I'm
too late to apply for this full
configuration,
so I'm going to minor in it.
I'm also minoring in AI.
It counts as one of them.
292 can also be one of them.
You need to take 281.
And then there's one elective.
You have choice between eight
classes,
eight each classes.
Not bad.
It's literally two extra classes
for me.
So I can't double count 492,
because it's actually a major
requirement for me.
because well there are a few
different tracks so yeah okay
that's what I thought but I
wanted to
Nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you too.
You guys?
No.
Perfect.
Yes.
Nice to meet you.
Okay.
Have a seat.
Hi,
there.
You got a spotlight for me.
Thank you.